A Guide to the Richmond (Va.) City Administration Records, 1782-1979
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond (Va.) City Administration Records, 1782-1979
The Library of Virginia
60 boxes (34.7 Cubic feet); 155 volumes
Richmond (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Common and City Council Journals, 1782-1883, use microfilm copies, Richmond (Va.) Reels 099-111. See "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Alternative Form Available
Common and City Council Journals, 1782-1883, use microfilm copies, Richmond (Va.) Reels 099-111.
Custodial History
Richmond (Va.) City Sergeant register, 1841-1846 and 1842-1844, with loose records, came to the Library of Virginia as a gift from the Virginia History Society (or the Virginia Museum of History and Culture) in 2021. The Virginia Historical Society received the original records in 1975 as a gift made by the New York State Library (Albany, N.Y.).
Acquisition Information
Richmond City Common Council, Alderman, and Ordinance volumes came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from the city of Richmond in 2015 under accession number 51527.
Loose Ordinance records came to Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from the city of Richmond in an undated accession.
City Sergeant records came to Library of Virginia in a transfer of court papers from the City of Richmond in 1997 under accessions 37370 and 37381.
An additional gift of City Sergeant records came from the Virginia Museum of History and Culture (Richmond, Va.) in 2022 under accession 53554.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type:
Richmond City Council
The Council largely took shape after the 1782 charter which called for the election of twelve property owners. Of these twelve one would be chosen mayor, one recorder, and a bicameral council comprised of four alderman, and six members of a Common Council. Together this group of elected officials became the Common Hall. In 1851 the Richmond charter changed to allow for the popular election of the mayor directly, as well as other municipals officers, but retained the bicameral council. This largely remained the structure until the 1947 charter which eliminated the bicameral council and instead created a nine-person council from which the council chose one of its member to serve as mayor and appointed a city manager. This system remained until 2004 when the mayor's position reverted to being popularly elected, serving as the chief administrative officer to the city with the nine-member city council acting as the main governing body.
City Sergeant Records
The City Sergeant(s) (sometimes spelt "Serjeant") were appointed and later elected positions that served municipalities in a function parallel to the sheriffs of Virginia's counties. The position originated from English law and was tied to the creation of a town/ cities independent court system, with the position of "serjeant to the City of Williamsburg" appearing as early as 1755. City Sergeant's generally acted as the chief police officer, and were charged with the issuing of subpoenas and warrants, seizure of property, collection of fees and other functions of the Hustings or Corporation court of a municipality.
Locality History:
City of Richmond, located between Henrico and Chesterfield Counties, was named by William Byrd (1674-1744), who envisioned the development of a city at the falls of the James River and with the help of William Mayo laid out the town in 1737. The name probably came from the English borough of Richmond upon Thames, which Byrd visited on several occasions. Richmond was established in 1742 and in 1779 was designated the capital of Virginia effective 30 April 1780. It was incorporated as a town, although "stiled the city of Richmond," in 1782 and was incorporated as a city in 1842. It served as the capital of the Confederacy from mid-1861 to April 1865. Richmond was enlarged by the annexation of Manchester (or South Richmond) in 1910, and by the addition of Barton Heights, Fairmount, and Highland Park in 1914. Further annexations from Chesterfield County occurred in 1942 and 1970.
Lost Locality: During the burning of Richmond on April 3, 1865, during the Civil War, Richmond circuit court judge John A. Meredith led efforts to save the circuit court records found at the State Court House. Rescuers successfully removed all the papers that were necessary to pending suits and many of the order books, but all of the wills and deed books were lost. Records of the superior court and circuit superior court of law and chancery were also destroyed. Most of the pre-Civil War Hustings Court records exist.
Scope and Content
Richmond (Va.) City Administration Records, 1782-1979, consists of records including minutes, journals, ordinances, records books, etc. created by various administrative offices and officials for the city of Richmond. These include:
Richmond City Council records, 1782-1979, which consist of records of the historic Common Hall comprised of the Common Council and Board of Alderman and modern City Council; records solely created by the Board of Alderman, records solely created by the Common Council.
City Council Records,1782-1979, consists of records created by bicameral Richmond's Common Hall which included the Board of Alderman and Common Council as well as other administrative officers, as well as records created by the modern system of the nine person city council. The majority of these records consists of ordinances inacted by the city council, but also includes some general records, accounts, budgets, and miscellaneous records.
Board of Alderman Records,1874-1948, consists of various volumes of the Board of Alderman Journal as well as indexes to the journals.
Common Council Records, 1808-1954, includes various volumes of the Common Council Journal as well as indexes to the journals.
City Sergeant Records, 1841-1913, consists of a City Sergeant Record Book, 1841-1846,kept by John M. Fergusson, City Sergeant, and Edward D. Eacho, N. E. Green, John Lynch, Francis Spragins, and Stanley J. Spragins, Deputy City Sergeants. The volume includes names of "runaway" enslaved persons and free Black and multiracial individuals as well as costs levied during imprisonment in the city jail. Also includes, City Sergeant Record Book, 1842-1844, kept by John M. Fergusson, City Sergeant, and John Lynch, Francis Spragins, and Stanley J. Spragins, Deputy City Sergeants. The volume includes names of persons imprisoned and costs levied during imprisonment in the city jail. Also includes, City Sergeant Record Book,1856-1858, undated, kept by city sergeant Thomas Underwood Dudley. In the first part of the volume, the city sergeant records his fees for the prosecution of court cases--serving writs, subpoenas, notices and summonses in chancery to both individuals and companies around the city and various counties and other cities in the state from April to September. The rest of the volume consists of committals to and releases from the city jail from 1856-1858. Notations were made about certain individuals upon their committal to the jail and were marked through and initialed by the city sergeant when the individual was released. Fees paid as a result of an individual's release from the city jail are also noted.
Also includes, Feebook,1902; a Fee Book, 1909-1913; and loose records, 1844-1851. The loose records include accounts concerning the operations of the City jail as well as Letter, n.d., of W[illiam] H. Armstrong to Richard [D.] Sanxay; list, 1849, of persons in the Richmond City Jail; affidavits, 1844, of R. T. Adams and William Lambert; petition, 1849, of Samuel Yancy as an insolvent debtor (witnessed by R. T. Adams); bond, 1850, of James A. Gibson to Daniel Hunt; summonses; and miscellany.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: City Council Records, 1782-1979, largely comprised of ordinances
Subseries A: Board of Alderman Records,1874-1948
Subseries B: Common Council Records,1808-1954
Series II: City Sergeant Records, 1841-1913. This set of records is not arranged in a particular manner with many of the records remaining unprocessed.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also: Richmond (Va.) Criminal Records, 1782-1963 (bulk 1945-1963) for commonwealth corresponds that correspond to the the City Sergeant Record books
See also: Richmond (Va.) Ended Causes, 1782-1951 (bulk 1900-1951) for additional criminial records unprocessed.
Records related to free and enslaved people of Richmond (Va.) and other localities are available through the Virginia Untold: The African American Narrative Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Additional Richmond (Va.) court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia.Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Richmond City is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Richmond City Court Records may be found in the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection on the Library of Virginia website.
Contents List
- City Council Records 1782-1979, 59 boxes (33 cubic feet); 151 volumes
  This series is prodominately ordinances created by the Richmond City Council. City Council records are indicated as records that were not explicity created by one of the houses of council. See SeriesI: Subseries A or B for records known to have been created specifally by the Board of Alderman or the Common Council.
  Chronological; boxed material is largely unprocessed
  - Common Hall Records 1782-1792 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
  - Ordinances 1782-1793 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
  - Common Hall Records 1793-1795 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
  - Ordinances 1793-1806 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
  - Ordinances 1804 March-1821 May
  - Ordinances 1806 October-1816 March
  - Ordinances 1816 April-1828 June
  - Ordinances 1828 July-1849 September
  - Ordinances 1849 November-1864 December
  - Council Papers 1860-1869
  - Ordinances 1865 January-1874 May
  - City Council Records 1866 October-1870 June
  - City Council Records 1870 July-1872 December
  - City Council Records 1873 January-1874 June
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1874 July-1876 July
  - Ordinances (Manchester) 1874-1900
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1876 July-1880 July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1880 July-1882 July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1882 July-1884 July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1884-1886
  - Franchises of the City of Richmond 1885-1899
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1886 July-1888 July
  - Council Papers--Ordinances 1886-1887; 1888-1889
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1888 July-1890 July
  - Ordinances 1889-1905
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1890 July-1892 July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1892 July-1894 July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1894 July-1896 July
  - Council Papers--Ordinances; Unfinis 1894-1896, 1898; 1876-1899
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1896 July-1898 July
  - Ordinances (Barton Heights) 1896-1900
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1898 July-1900 July
  - Ordinances (Barton Heights) 1898-1914
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1900 July-1902 July
  - Ordinances (Fairmount) 1900-1906
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1902 July-1904 July
  - Ordinances 1902 May-1906 April
  - Ordinances (Manchester) 1902-1910
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1904 August-1906 June
  - Joint Session of Common Council of Board of Aldermen 1904-1940
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1905 May-1907 Aprilil
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1906 July-1908 August
  - Ordinances 1906 May-1908 April
  - Ordinances 1908 May-1909 November
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1908 September-1910 August
  - Ordinances 1909 December-1910 July
  - Ordinances (Highland Park) 1909-1912
  - Ordinances, Bonds, and Court Papers 1909-1914
  - Ordinances 1910 August-1911 December
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1910 September-1912 August
  - Ordinances and reports 1910s-1970s
  - Ordinances 1912 January-1913 June
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1912 September-1914 August
  - Ordinances (North Richmond) 1913
  - Ordinances 1913 July-1915 February
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1914 September-1916 August
  - Ordinances 1915 March -August 1916
  - Ordinances 1916 October-1918 March
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1916 September-1918 August
  - Ordinances 1918 April -1920 January
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1918 September-1920 August
  - Ordinances 1920 February-May 1921
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1920 September-1922 August
  - Ordinances 1921 June- 1922 March
  - Ordinances 1922 April-1923 March
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1922 September-1924 August
  - Ordinances 1922-1924
  - Ordinances 1923 April-September
  - Ordinances 1923 October-1924 June
  - Ordinances 1924 July-1925 March
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1924 September-1926 August
  - Ordinances 1925 April-December
  - Ordinances 1926 August-1927 March
  - Ordinances 1926 January-July
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1926 September-1928 August
  - Ordinances 1927 April-November
  - Ordinances 1927 December-1928 July
  - Ordinances 1928 August-1929 February
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1928 September-1930 August
  - Ordinances 1929 March-Septembertember
  - Ordinances 1929 October-1930 April
  - Ordinances 1930 May-1931 April
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1930 September-1932 August
  - Ordinances 1930-1932
  - Ordinances 1931 May-1932 June
  - Expense Accounts, Budget Ordinances 1931-1935
  - Ordinances 1932 July-1933 October
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1932 September-1934 August
  - Ordinances 1933 November-1934 December
  - Ordinances 1933-1934
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1934 September-1936 August
  - Ordinances 1934-1938
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1936 September-1938 August
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1938 September-1940 August
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1938-1948
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1940 September-1942 August
  - Joint Session of Board of Aldermen and Common Council 1940 September-1948 August
  - Ordinances 1940-1943
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1942 September-1944 August
  - Ordinances 1944-1946
  - Ordinances 1944-1946
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1946 September-1948 January
  - Ordinances 1946-1948
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1947 December-1948 August
  - Council Journal 1948 June-1951 June
  - Ordinances 1948 September-1951 February
  - Ordinances 1951 March-1952 November
  - Ordinances 1952 November-1954 March
  - Ordinances 1954 March-1955 June
  - Council Journal 1954 September-1957 August
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1955 June-1957 January
  - Ordinances 1957 January-1958 August
  - Council Journal 1957-1960
  - Ordinances, Personnel, Miscellaneous Records 1957-1974
  - Ordinances 1958-1960
  - Council Journal 1960 December-1964 June
  - Ordinances 1960 May-1961 October
  - Ordinances 1961 October-1963 June
  - Ordinances 1963 June-1965 February
  - Council Journal 1964 June-1968 March
  - Ordinances 1965 February-1966 May
  - Ordinances 1966 June 13-1968 March 25
  - Council Journal 1968 April-1971 March
  - Ordinances 1968-1969
  - Ordinances 1969 September-1971 February
  - Ordinances (70-1--70-200) 1970
  - Ordinances (70-201--70-349) 1970
  - Ordinances (71-1--71-170) 1971
  - Ordinances (71-171--71-290) 1971
  - Council Journal 1971 April-1973 December
  - Ordinances 1971 March-1972 June
  - Ordinances (71-291--72-70) 1971-1972
  - Ordinances (72-201--72-310) 1972
  - Ordinances (72-71--72-200) 1972
  - Ordinances (73-121--73-220) 1972
  - Ordinances (73-1--73-120) 1972
  - Ordinances (73-221--72-320) 1972
  - Ordinances 1972-1973
  - Council Journal 1973 December-1976 October
  - Ordinances (74-111--74-220) 1974
  - Ordinances (74-1--74-110) & Motions 1974
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1974 January-1975 June
  - Ordinances, (75.151--75-280) 1975
  - Ordinances, (75-1--75.150) 1975
  - Ordinances, (75-281--75-300) 1975
  - Ordinances, (75-301--75-350) 1975
  - Ordinances and Resolutions 1975 July-1976 October
  - Ordinances 1976 November-1977 March
  - Council Journal 1976 October-1979 September
  - Index to Joint Session of Common Council and Board of Aldermen undated
  - Board of Alderman records, 1874-1948, 23 volumes
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1874 July-1878 June
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1878 July-1887 January
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1887 February-1892 June
    - Index to Board of Alderman Journal 1887 February-1892 June
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1892 July-1897 April
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1892 July-1897 April
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1897 May-1901 December
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1897 May-1901 December
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1902 January-1906 March
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1902 January-1906 March
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1906 April-1909 April
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1906 April-1909 April
    - Index to Board of Alderman Journal 1909 May-1911 October
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1909 May-1911 October
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1911 November-1914 October
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1911 November-1914 October
    - Board of Aldermen Records 1914 October-1918 August
    - Board of Alderman Journal 1914 October-1918 August
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1918 September-1923 December
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1924-1929
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1930 January-1937 July
    - Board of Aldermen Journal 1937 July-1944 March
    - Index to Board of Aldermen Journal 1944 March-1948 August
  - Common Council records, 1808-1954, 40 volumes
    - Common Council Records 1808-1813 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
    - Common Council Records 1808-1816 [MICROFILM, Reel 99]
    - Common Council Records 1874 July-1878 June
    - Common Council Records 1878 July-1883 December
    - Common Council Journal 1884 January-1887 March
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1887 April-1890 December
    - Common Council Journal 1887 April-1890 November
    - Common Council Journal 1890 December-1894 April
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1890 December-1894 April
    - Common Council Journal 1894 May-1896 November
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1894 May-1896 November
    - Common Council Journal 1896 December-1899 September
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1896-1899
    - Common Council Journal 1899 October-1902 November
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1899 October-1902 November
    - Common Council Journal 1902 December-1905 May
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1902 December-1905 May
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1905 May-1907 April
    - Common Council Journal 1907 April-1908 October
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1907 April-1908 October
    - Common Council Journal 1908 November-1910 May
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1908 November-1910 May
    - Common Council Journal 1910 June-1911 October
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1910 June-1911 October
    - Common Council Journal 1911 November-1913 May
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1911 November-1913 May
    - Common Council Journal 1913 June-1915 April
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1913 June-1915 April
    - Common Council Journal 1915 May-1917 May
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1915 May-1917 May
    - Common Council Journal 1917 June-1918 August
    - Index to Common Council Journal 1917 June-1918 August
    - Common Council Journal 1918 September-1922 February
    - Common Council Journal 1922 March-1925 April
    - Common Council Journal 1925 April-1928 June
    - Common Council Journal 1928 July-1931 September
    - Common Council Journal 1932 January-1936 July
    - Common Council Journal 1936 July-1939 June
    - Common Council Journal 1939 July-1942 June
    - Common Council Journal 1942 July-1946 August
    - Common Council Journal 1946 September-1948 August
    - Common Council Journal 1951 June-1954 August
- City Sergeant Records, 1841-1913, 1 box (1 cubic feet); 4 volumes
  Chronological
  - City Sergeant Record Book, 1841-1846
  - City Sergeant Record Book, 1842-1844
  - City Sergeant Record Book, 1856-1858
  - Loose City Sergeant Records, 1844-1851
  - City Sergeant's Fee Book, 1902
  - City Sergeant's Fee Book, 1909-1913